<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The passion sermon at Pauls-Crosse vpon Good-Friday last, Aprill 7. 1626. By Thomas Ailesbury.</title>
            <author>Ailesbury, Thomas, fl. 1622-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113678</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848909</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 617:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The passion sermon at Pauls-Crosse vpon Good-Friday last, Aprill 7. 1626. By Thomas Ailesbury.</title>
                  <author>Ailesbury, Thomas, fl. 1622-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M[iller] for Richard Moore, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstans Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14031:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14031:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PASSION SERMON AT PAVLS-CROSSE, vpon GOOD-FRIDAY laſt, Aprill 7. 1626.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Ailesbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sanguis Chriſti eſt Clauis Paradiſi,</hi> 
               <bibl>Tertullian.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Richard Moore,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Saint <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 1626.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14031:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14031:2"/>
            <head>THE PASSION SERMON at <hi>Pauls</hi>-Croſſe, vpon <hi>Good-Friday</hi> laſt, Aprill 7. 1626.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 2.8.</hi>
                  </bibl> Had they knowne, they would not haue crucified the Lord of glory.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Paul,</hi> the Trumpe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Proclaimer of the Goſpell, who on earth ſate at <hi>Gamaliels</hi> feet, and in a diuine rapture was aſſumed into a higher Schoole in Heauen, where hee gained the audience of vnſpeakable myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The deputed, deligated Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Apoſtle of the Gentiles,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> made <hi>Chriſt crucified</hi> his preaching, his learning, and his glory. The ſubiect of his preaching, <hi>We preach Christ crucified;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6, 14.</note> the obiect of his glory, <hi>God forbid I ſhould glory ſaue in the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The Sap of his learning, <hi>I determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not to know any thing, ſaue Ieſus Chriſt, and him cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</hi> Very well may the death of life, the end of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the Obſequies of him that could not dye make
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14031:3"/>worke for this great Apoſtle. Tis learning enough to ſit at the Croſſe by the feete of Chriſt; no Schoole to <hi>Caluary,</hi> no Chaire to the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> no Doctor vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> no Leſſon to <hi>him crucified.</hi> This is <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Chaire, <hi>Dauids</hi> Key, and <hi>Solomons</hi> Throne, wherein I know not if the loue of God the Father was more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to exhibit, or the Will of God the Sonne more prompt to this propitiatory expedition. <hi>Oblatus eſt quia voluit.</hi> And Chriſt would neuer haue beene ſo willing, but he knew it to be of ſoueraigne vſe for mankinde: <hi>miſit redemptionem; Hee ſent redemption to his people,</hi> profitable for vs, but it coſt him deare, <hi>redemit ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> it was the price of bloud. Were euery Starre a world, here is plenteous redemption for them all; of great extent, which reacheth vnto all, <hi>Omnia trahit ad ſeipſum,</hi> In this good all our felicity doth conſent; the effuſion of his Bloud not without paine, that paine without paralell, <hi>Was there euer ſorrow like to my ſorrow?</hi> Paine concomitated with ſhame, <hi>Cum iniquis reputatus eſt,</hi> he makes vp the number of the wicked, as vniuſt as could be, <hi>Sicut ouis ad occiſionem,</hi> as vnkind as might be, maſſacred by his owne Nation. A people whom God had ſequeſtred to himſelfe, yet when we view the record of their liues, they make it good that their Election was not of workes but of grace. They had <hi>Abraham</hi> to their Father: could God to that Patriarke, vpon the exerciſe of his omnipotency, forge or raiſe a more flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ceneration? The <hi>Meſsias,</hi> the perfume of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings, the bloud of their Sacrifices, the fire of their Holocauſts, ſhadowed in their Ceremonies, fore-ſpoken by their Prophets, all this could not diſpell that miſt of darkneſſe which ſetled vpon their hearts; <hi>Si enim cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouiſſent:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14031:3"/>for, <hi>had they knowne, they would not haue crucified the Lord of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts and perſons of this Text are two fold: Firſt, the perſons nocent, the <hi>Iewes.</hi> Secondly, the party Innocent, <hi>The Lord of glory.</hi> Of them the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh; firſt, by way of ſuppoſition; <hi>Si cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſent, Had they knowne.</hi> Secondly, by way of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the ſequel inferreth, <hi>non cognouerunt,</hi> they haue not knowne him. In the ſecond part there are two branches. 1. The <hi>Indignitie</hi> of the <hi>Paſsion,</hi> the worſt that might be; <hi>They crucified.</hi> 2. The <hi>dignitie</hi> of the <hi>Patient,</hi> the beſt that could be; <hi>the Lord of glory.</hi> Theſe pillars muſt carrie my meditations, and your attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I begin with the <hi>Iewes</hi> ignorance, and ſhall end with their malice to the <hi>Lord of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Iewes</hi> proceed againſt their <hi>Meſsias</hi> out of errour. Ignorance was that cloud,
<note place="margin">The firſt part of their ignorance.</note> in which all the ſtormes that fell vpon our Sauiours head were ingendred; ſo the due puniſhments which hung o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their heads, and by the tradition of iuſt reuenge vpon their children, to them were vailed; <hi>Ieruſalem ſi cognouiſſes &amp; haec,</hi> a Citie in this miſerable, in that ſhe did not vnderſtand her approaching miſery.</p>
            <p>COuld the <hi>Iewes</hi> bee ignorant of their <hi>Meſsias?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Iewes <hi>could not ſee Chriſt by the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </note> They were <hi>men,</hi> and vpon the firſt <hi>Man</hi> God ſtampt his Image; as the Sunne is guilded with light, ſo the Soule was engrauen with knowledge: but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and his wife, ambitious to enlarge their Science, would ſteale it forth of the ſides of an Apple, that all was cancelled, and obliterated by their fall, and a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14031:4"/>due to their pride to <hi>know as Gods,</hi> was to bee as ignorant as beaſts. Thus man, an Egregious crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was yoaked with beaſts, who may ſay truly, what God Ironically,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce Adam factus eſt quaſi vnus e no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> ſee, man is become as one of vs; here's little light left for the <hi>Iewes</hi> to ſee their <hi>Meſsias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man naturally endeuours to repaire theſe loſſes, to ſet downe ſome thing in the naked tables of his ſoule, the corporall organs no ſooner giue leaue to the ſoule to vnfold it ſelfe, but it readily makes loue to knowledge. Dame natures beſt ſcholler makes vs no leſſe deſirous then happy in the enioying.</p>
            <p>Yet without ſupernall reuelation <hi>Philoſophie</hi> beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not <hi>Theologie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc doctus Plato neſciuit, hoc elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens Demoſtenes ignorauit. Platoes</hi> learning could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer towre ſo high, nor <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> eloquence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it. Were euery <hi>Iew</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> well read in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> learning, and <hi>Aegypt</hi> was then the worlds <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademy; Greece</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine</hi> had not yet ſpoiled her of that Iewell: ſuch Herbaliſts as <hi>Salomon,</hi> whoſe skill reacheth from the Cedar to the Thiſtle: ſuch Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries to Nature, that the earth ſhould not quake, nor the Sea paſſe her bounds, except their Art ſhould impale the one, confirme the other; or that the voice of thunder could not be heard in our Land, but they ſo well acquainted with it, as if they had made that Canon, and charged it with that Bullet; or the Clouds not ſet on fire by lightning without the ſparkes of their inuention, to kindle them; or thoſe Chriſtall bottles of the aire thin as the liquor they containe, could not emptie their moiſt burthens vpon the earth without their prognoſtication, or the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14031:4"/>power of ſome domineering planet to vnſtop them; could they number the Starres, read their meaning in their faces, I load your patience: what of all this? This is a wiſe madneſſe, ſaith <hi>Iuſtin Martyr;</hi> a buſie vanitie, ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi> and a curious fanſie.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 38 4.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe men dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken counſell by words without knowledge. Where waſt thou when I laid the foundation of the earth? declare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 38.25.26.</note> 
               <hi>If thou haſt vnderſtanding, who laid the corner ſtone; who ſhut vp the Sea within doores when I made a cloud the garment thereof, and the thicke darkeneſſe a ſwadling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and ſaid, hitherto ſhalt thou come, here ſhall thy proud waues be ſtaied. The Lord weigheth the winds and waters by meaſure, maketh a decree for raine, and a way for lightning and thunder.</hi> Thus their owne Art is their owne labyrinth, much more will the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent truth of the Goſpell amaze them. <hi>Pauls</hi> Lecture at <hi>Athens</hi> was a new Doctrine neuer heard of there, the Inſcription vpon their altar <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of their ignorance.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>Wee ſpeake the wiſedome of God hidden in a Myſterie. Where is the wiſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Where is the Scribe? Where is the Diſputer of this world? Hath not God made fooliſh the wiſedome of this world? I will deſtroy the wiſedome of the wiſe, and bring to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the vnderſtanding of the Prudent.</hi> The ladder of humaine wiſedome is too ſhort to ſcale the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt; Wee preach Chriſt crucified, vnto the Iewes a ſtumbling blocke, vnto the Greekes fooliſhneſſe:</hi> the myſterie whereof was wiſedome beyond their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, knowledge beyond their learning, and a worke beyond their time; were the <hi>Iewes</hi> as wiſe as the wiſeſt Philoſophers, yet <hi>non cognouerunt,</hi> that knowledge will not lend them Spectacles to ſee <hi>the Lord of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14031:5"/>
            <p> But the <hi>Iewes</hi> were the Secretaries of Heauen, they <hi>haue Moſes and the Prophets;</hi> to them were theſe diuine Oracles committed, <hi>The Lord was knowne in Iury, and his Name great in Iſrael,</hi> this Sunne was in that Ecliptike, this light in that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen. If all other lights be an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> falie and dimnie, heres a Starre from Heauen that will neuer faile them: man to the attainment of a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall end needs a ſupernaturall meane, the naturall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, <hi>Non ſufficit viatori,</hi> will neuer ſhine bright enough to be our ſafe conduct to theſe cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall truthes.
<note place="margin">In Prolog. ſent.</note> 
               <hi>Percipit per naturalem potentiam, non per naturalem agentem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Scotus.</hi> It may be the Caske to reſerue, neuer the light without a greater light to deſcry them. Hee keeps his Chaire in Heauen that dictates theſe leſſons. Illiterate Apoſtles, in whom the Creator to qualifie them with gifts wrought a new creation, that ſuddenly from all ſimple they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all wiſe, the Iewes therefore hauing the Key of Scriptures, what myſteries will not that vnlocke?</p>
            <p>Come then, lets ſee what light the Scripture giues to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> here are contained a cloud of Propheſies, the day would faile me to ſuruay them.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Semen muli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris, &amp;c.</hi> twas but young dayes when God firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged himſelfe to mercy, that a Childe ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire thoſe breaches the mother occaſioned. The promiſe is renewed to <hi>Abraham:</hi> vpon his ſeede the bleſſed one is entailed, but the <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> is inlarged vnto all nations, in the miraculous birth and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudy facrifice of <hi>Iſaak</hi> was a viſion of the birth and death of the worlds redeemer, <hi>Abraham ſaw my day and reioyced.</hi> What will the Iewes ſay to <hi>Iacobs Shilo.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14031:5"/>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 49.</note> When in <hi>Chriſts</hi> time the <hi>Scepter</hi> was wreſted out of the Iewes hands: Their King a beneficiary, and precarious King: With all their hearts they wiſhed for the Meſſias, though their conceits could no otherwiſe imploy <hi>him</hi> then to quit them of the Romane yoke. <hi>Dauid</hi> was the root out of which this branch did flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; What Ditties did <hi>Iſraels</hi> chiefe Chanter war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vpon his Sonne, his Lord. The manner of his death, the cry vpon the Croſſe, his Paſſion, and his skorne are the contents of that Euangelicall 22. Pſalme, <hi>I am powred out like water: a worme and no man: I may tell all my bones: they part my Garments in ſunder, &amp;c.</hi> So plaine, that the wicked Iewes had no way to put out the eyes of that Propheſie, then by offering violence to the ſacred Text. And had rather poſterity ſhould finde <hi>non-ſenſe,</hi> then their cruelty recorded. <hi>Eſay,</hi> the flower of ſpeech and Propheſie, who ſeemes to contex a Hiſtory, not write a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>Surely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>hee hath borne our griefes and carried our ſorrowes; hee was wounded for our tranſgreſsions, hee opened not his mouth, he is brought like a Lambe to the ſlaughter, the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of vs all.</hi> And to giue the Scribes and Prieſts their due, they could by this light blazen the Tribe, Family,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.</note> and <hi>place of his birth.</hi> For when the <hi>Starre</hi> diſpeared, the Propheſies by them applyed to the Sages of the Eaſt, were <hi>Starres,</hi> to conduce their feet to worſhip there, as ſwift as <hi>Herods</hi> to goe ſhed bloud there. How then could the Iewes be ignorant?</p>
            <p>Very well, for Propheſies are but empty ſounds, <hi>Volant &amp; auolant,</hi> the flye and dye; beate the eare,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14031:6"/>not the heart, if the Holy Ghoſt bee not preſent to pierce it. No breaking open theſe Seales, no vnlock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe myſteries without <hi>Dauids</hi> Key. The right honourable Eunuch, Treaſurer to the Queen of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> ſought for a better treaſure at that time to be found at Hieruſalem, <hi>nec Sanctior ſum hoc Eunucho, nec ſtudioſior.</hi> Can our diligence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare with his, who vnderwent a tedious iourney, and in that deuout Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage made the Scripture his companion?
<note place="margin">Hieron ad Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin.</note> 
               <hi>Et cum verba Domini lingua volueret, labijs perſonaret; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabat cum, quem in libro neſciens venerabatur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Heirom.</hi> He read the Prophet without diuine Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and with an implicite deuotion adored whom he knew not. <hi>Philip</hi> layeth open Ieſus, that lay hid in the letter, for the common place of his Meditations was the very Paſſion of Ieſus. But the Iewes had no ſacred Spirit, no <hi>Philip</hi> to expound theſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, their proud conceits cheating their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as ſome fooliſh Mountebankes were ignorant of what they profeſſed; and which (I cannot ſpeake without ſtomake) were ignorant of their ignorance: for all this to them <hi>Moſes</hi> is vailed; I know who hath ſaid it,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>When Moſes is read, the vaile is vpon their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVHat of this,
<note place="margin">3 They know not the Meſſias in our Sauiours perſon.</note> will the Iew reply, wee are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Scripture, the Propheſies flye not out of our ſight, the Meſſias we expect, and hope he is not long a comming, then a ruſh for this <hi>Roman dominion;</hi> but is it poſſible Ieſus ſhould bee the man? borne of meane parentage, his education obſcure, himſelfe followed by the meaneſt; we muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14031:6"/>by better euidence, our Rulers vpon ſuch ſlender proofes are too wiſe to truſt him. But no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to diſtruſt him, a threefold cord of witneſſes is not eaſily broken: Chriſt, beſides the written, had the liuing Word of his mouth, ſupported by his famous Acts to ſpeake for him. <hi>Scrutamini Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) Search theſe Volumes, and if I am not recorded there, neuer credit me more: his aſtoniſhing words and conuincing workes, what mettall were the Iewes compoſed off, that theſe would not ſoften?</p>
            <p>What was <hi>Chriſts</hi> life but a Commentary, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of the fore-running Propheſies. The <hi>Law</hi> was but a ſhadow; <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſubſtance, the <hi>good thing to come. In the volume of thy Law it is written of me, &amp;c.</hi> not a line therein but tends vnto Chriſt the Center, his birth of a <hi>Virgin-mother,</hi> cradle ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, when he fled that could not goe, the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of his preaching, his miraculous cures, vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his Fathers Temple from pollution, &amp;c. all are filed which were in him fulfilled. Let vs areſt our ſelues awhile vpon his foretold Paſſions, when Chriſt rode in triumph towards his Croſſe, hee did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtride an Aſſes backe without a Propheſie to helpe him vp; <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>thy King commeth riding vpon an Aſſes fole. Indas</hi> makes his merchandiſe of him, the price of bloud is pitcht by one Prophet, and the man of bloud deſcribed by another;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lach</hi> 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>a goodly price</hi> that I was prized of them, euen <hi>thirty pieces:</hi> ſee the difference, GOD values man at his owne Bloud, man his God at thirty pence. The Betrayer is betrayed by deſcription, <hi>My familiar and friend, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 41.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14031:7"/>
               <hi>hath conſpired againſt me.</hi> All his Diſciples ſhall turne Cowards, a Propheſie had ſounded that retreat, <hi>I will ſtrike the Shepherd and the ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered;</hi> dye he muſt, for the Meſſias muſt be ſlaine, and that in a grieuous manner, to make good the Type, <hi>he muſt be lifted vp;</hi> then faſtened with nailes; <hi>They haue pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my hands and my feet,</hi> vpon a Croſſe, <hi>Dominus triumphauit eligno,</hi> which reading <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> imbrace. If they plough vpon his backe with whips, thoſe Furrowes are recorded. No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell the Souldiers riflle for his garments, that vailed couetouſneſſe of Lots an euent in it ſelfe contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.</note> in the Propheſie certaine, <hi>for my veſtments they did caſt lots.</hi> What will the Iew ſay now? Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies not accompliſhed, <hi>ambiguitates ſunt &amp; anigmata,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Irenaeus</hi>) are darke Clouds, but in the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment thoſe Clouds are diſperſed, they become Hiſtories. Obdurate Iewes! ſhew vs but a man in whom all the Propheſies were fulfilled, and any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie left vnfulfilled in our Sauiours perſon, and we will ſuppoſe ſome probability to march on your ſide: why then? (knowing what the <hi>Iewes</hi> did know) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo foule a fact will our Apoſtle finde and returne <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> Yet one propheſie had not beene accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht, if the <hi>Iewes</hi> had knowne it, that they muſt be the men to imbrew their hands in the bloud of their <hi>Meſsias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>They</hi> glory in the act, are ſo confident, that were it to doe againe, their Conſcience would make no ſcruple to reiterate it; as deeming the ſame a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter piece of obedience. In killing of his Diſciples they thought to merit at the hands of God, but in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14031:7"/>killing of his ſonne to ſuper-errogate, and in a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate affectation of Ignorance, ſollicite for that blood vpon their heads, which <hi>Pilate</hi> waſhed from his hands; and are ſo farre from ſorrow, that holding one life too little to take from him, onely they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he hath no more: their Malice is ſo hereditary, that if Chriſt ſhould reuiue himſelfe daily, to ſaue the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> a labour, daily would they <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Groſſe miſtake there was then in the perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 The Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Ieſus did not remoue their ignorance.</note> who in their owne verdict was not tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſinne; but that they could not collect what he was by his miracles, they are to mee a miracle of ſottiſh infidelity; <hi>Iudaei ſigna petunt,</hi> their curioſitie was ſet vpon miracles; now they might take their fill. Tell me, what was he?
<note place="margin">Arnob.</note> 
               <hi>Cuius Iuſſu ipſi Daemones in hominum viſceribus merſt, &amp; cooperti poſſeſsione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debant:</hi> The very Dinels inuiſcerated in men, at the ſound of his Imperiall word, yeeld vp poſſeſſion, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their habitations, as if their houſes had beene on fire ouer their heads: Confeſſion is their penance, with an yeelding voyce they yellow out, <hi>Thou art the Sonne of God: Intelligunt diaboli quod non intelligunt Iudaei,</hi> as <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſpake of the <hi>Arians;</hi> that power the diuels aſcribe to God which the <hi>Iewes</hi> to the Diuels; ſurely Sathan is a greater polititian then to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe with ciuill diſcord. Was <hi>hee</hi> an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Man,</hi> who with the trident of his word becalmes the Seas, paues them with ſolidity to a confirmed path for himſelfe and <hi>Peter</hi> to walke on; the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors amazed cry out, what manner of man was this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14031:8"/>to whom the dumbe creatures ſpeake ſuch obedience. Surely hee another <hi>Neptune</hi> was then whom Poets faine:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arnob. cra. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes lib</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Poſt liminto vitam reſtituens animas efflatas iuſsit in diem lucidam remeare:</hi> Chriſts call awakes <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the graue, vnites what death for foure dayes had diuorced, the ſpirit returneth to its old moald, and by a new <hi>Metempſychoſis,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (ſuch which <hi>Pythagoras</hi> neuer drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of) the ſame ſoule reenters into the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. This Miracle reconciles enuie, enuie a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and for a further concluſion, <hi>They</hi> will ſee if <hi>God</hi> can dye or noe. When the Conſpirators came armed to apprehend him, who expected not declined them, the breath of his mouth as a mighty tempeſt, leuels them with the earth. A <hi>Roman Cohort</hi> driuen backe at a word? <hi>Nec vox hominem ſonat:</hi> could not his ſpeech betray him? without flattery they might haue applauded, not the voyce of man, but God. <hi>Quid poterit Mateſt as eius iudicatura, cuius hoc poterat humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas Iudicanda,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo.</hi> When <hi>Peter</hi> with a blow had lopt off <hi>Malchus</hi> eare, the diuorced peece is glew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to its former place, <hi>Chriſt</hi> reforming what himſelfe had formed, and that fleſh knowing whoſe potſheard it was, is no ſooner touched with Gods finger, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine reſtored, yet this Phyſitians pay was cruelty.</p>
            <p>Thus to recapitulate all, 1. not humane ſcience, 2. not reuealed propheſies, 3. though accompliſhed in Chriſts perſon: 4. confirmed with the working of Miracles could open their eyes, but in <hi>ſeeing they did not ſee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquia.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. God hath ſent them the ſpirit of ſlumber.</hi> Theſe Euidences led them to know the <hi>Meſsias</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but not the <hi>Myſterie</hi> in the <hi>Deitie,</hi> but with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14031:8"/>leaue to <hi>Aquinas</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> held the Deitie inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the <hi>Meſsias:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſoſtome in loc.</note> or they knew not <hi>Crucifixionis myſterium.</hi> The <hi>Meſsias</hi> to vndergoe ſo ignominious a death, to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> and be <hi>crucified vnder Pontius Pilate,</hi> could neuer come within the <hi>Iewiſh Creede.</hi> The vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar <hi>Iew</hi> conceiued well, but not truly, of him; yet ſomewhat popiſh loath to leaue the tradition of his fathers. The more illuminate Doctors had greater knowledge, but with greater pride and malice, which did extinguiſh it. Their <hi>Theory</hi> was vertiginous, ſwom in the braine, there floating without anchor, and was of no credit with the will. They cauelled at his preaching, traduced his perſon, ſlandered his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, fathering them vpon diuels. God onely hath the key which vnlocks the heart, Faith is in his owne cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie, and he diſtributs it to whom he will. Yet their ignorance was a ſinne; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> led away with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate zeale, was made thereby the chiefe of ſinners, though qualified for mercy. In the <hi>Iewes</hi> their knowledge ſhall accuſe them not acquit them, they knew enough to condemne them, but not enough to to ſaue them.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Diuine decree</hi> for ſlaying of the Lambe was out, which nailed him ſurer to the <hi>Croſſe</hi> then the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> nailes, and thereby ſealed to an infallible ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: how then can the <hi>determinate counſell of God</hi> be ſet vpon the contingent knowledge of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> The <hi>Ieſuites</hi> piece all with a <hi>Scient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a media,</hi> whereby God holds his hands from decreeing, till either in <hi>ſe</hi> or in <hi>re,</hi> he obſerueth the voluminous foldings, and pleating of the Will of man, and paſſeth his decree accordingly: So he knew Conditionately what the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14031:9"/>
               <hi>Iewes</hi> would haue done vpon better knowledge. The <hi>Schoolemen</hi> content themſelues with <hi>Scientta ſimplicis Intelligentiae,</hi> whoſe obiect is <hi>Ens poſsibile,</hi> but not <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum,</hi> goes as farre as poſſibility can goe: and <hi>Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia viſionis,</hi> whereby God perceiueth all things that are and ſhall be. Betwixt them crouds in <hi>Scientia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and participates of both: as it precedeth the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> decree hath relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the former; but as the effect may come to paſſe, if the condition were fulfilled, commeth neerer to that of <hi>Viſion;</hi> a ſpiders web, a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fanſie, and <hi>Ieſuites</hi> darling; pretended by <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeca</hi> to be found in <hi>Ariſtotles Metaphyſicks,</hi> which to eſtabliſh a freedome of will in man, deſtroyes it in God; for God may not decree till he ſeeth what man will doe; and what man will doe, God is bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine accordingly.</p>
            <p>But without this groundleſſe ſubtilty, truth will ſhew it ſelfe. Neceſſary euents as they flow from the firſt cauſe, in reſpect of the ſecond cauſes may admit contingency; both in the effect may concurre with no diſſonant harmony; for 1. Many effects are immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſecond cauſes, which in reſpect of the firſt cauſe are mutable; the Sunne is a fixed Planet vnto <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> ſtands ſtill to behold his conqueſts, flyes back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at the ſight of <hi>Ahaz dyall,</hi> yet <hi>ex neceſsitate natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> conſtantly circleth about the heauens in the Orbe his Chariot, and is neuer tyred with that diurnall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe. 2. Many Effects mutable in the ſecond cauſes, but immutable in the firſt cauſe: the confirmed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels by nature ſubiect to change by grace determined in goodneſſe; collapſed <hi>Adam</hi> in reſpect of the diuine Preſcience his fall was neceſſary, but in himſelfe moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14031:9"/>contingent, ſo for Chriſt, his Father from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie markt him to the ſlaughter by his decree; yet our Sauiour offred himſelfe as willingly as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did kill him, although <hi>non inde volunt as interficien divnde moriendi;</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> had not the ſame end in killing as <hi>Chriſt</hi> in dying. Our Redeemer then did ſuffer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily; <hi>neceſsitate finis,</hi> in three reſpects ſaith <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas:</hi> 1. for vs, to procure our freedome,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin. part.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 40.</note> 
               <hi>Oportet exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari; The ſonne of man muſt bee lifted vp, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh.</hi> Secondly, for himſelfe, to make way for Glory: <hi>Opertet Chriſtum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti; ought not Chriſt to ſuffer theſe things, and ſo to enter into his glory.</hi> Thirdly, to anſwer his Fathers Decree: <hi>filius hominis ſicut definitum eſt vadit; The Sonne of man truely goeth as it is written of him.</hi> Thus the <hi>Iewes</hi> were as free as ignorant, euery way guilty; neither Gods all ſeeing decree, nor their blinded ignorance ſhall excuſe them from that which followeth; <hi>They crucified the Lord of glory;</hi> which is the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>THE <hi>Iewes</hi> for long were, as I may ſay,
<note place="margin">The firſt branch the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>They.</hi>
               </note> the fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of heauen; if deliuerances, miracles and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are pledges of mercy, neuer was people ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared, or God more exuberant to any Nation, <hi>non taliter ſecit, &amp;c.</hi> yet they were an ill complexioned people, of a rebellious and churliſh temper. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is hardned and ſcourged to tame them; neuer was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prince ſo ſubdued with wonders, yet they aſcribe their deliuerance to a Calfe, and though thoſe Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were Emblems of a <hi>Diuiner power,</hi> and did ſpeake a ſupreame <hi>Deitie;</hi> they proſtrate themſelues vnto an Idol beholding for its Godhead, to the curious <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14031:10"/>God ſent his Prophets, which ſealed their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies with their bloud; long had Chriſt been ſlaine in them, now they kill him in himſelfe. Thoſe to this were tolerable Aſſaſinates; for fleſht in their bloud, they conſpire againſt the <hi>Lord of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt needs augment his torments, that his owne people ſhould degenerate into Traitors, not a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi> but a <hi>Iew,</hi> not a <hi>Iew</hi> alone, but <hi>Iudas</hi> his Apoſtle. The <hi>Gentiles</hi> were Idolaters, the <hi>Iewes</hi> like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, cruell, <hi>Iudas</hi> was a man, and <hi>homo Deo lupus,</hi> no maruell theſe doe like themſelues. God his father, and Chriſt moſt deare vnto himſelfe, are priuie to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of all this; conſpiracy, and danger on all hands, Treaſon, treaſon, neuer the like, of Iew and Gentile, Souldiers and Apoſtle, father and ſonne, heauen and earth, <hi>Singuli non perdunt, per dunt omnes;</hi> all coniure againſt this lambe to lead him to the ſlaughter. The Father, <hi>I haue ſmitten him:</hi> The Sonne, <hi>I lay downe my life for my ſheepe;</hi> the <hi>Iew, crucifie him;</hi> the <hi>Gentile,</hi> in <hi>Pilate</hi> condemning him, the Earth gaping for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, the heauens waiting for reſtitution. Thus a ſonne deliuered of his father, yeelding himſelfe, a Prince ſlaine of his people, the Nations coniure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bleſſed one of Nations, heauens diſpoyle him of his throne, the earth of his footſtoole: but in what had Chriſt offended himſelfe, to lay hands vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his owne perſon, <hi>abnegauit ſeipſum non quod debuit pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis plenus, ſed quod voluit plenus charitatis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian:</hi> no need to deny himſelfe for ſin, but choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hate himſelfe then deſiſt from louing vs.</p>
            <p>All Chriſts life a continuall paſſion, baniſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had the vſe of his legges, in preachings often,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14031:10"/>in faſtings, and temptations often, reſtleſſe, harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>&amp; in vita paſsiuam habuit actionem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in morte paſsionem actiuam ſuſtinuit,</hi> and though the <hi>Iewes</hi> could not lay hold on him till the houre was come, yet before-hand they crucifie his reputation: but all theſe to that which followed were but the beginning of ſorrowes. Let vs trace his footſteps, though with <hi>Peter</hi> we follow him a farre off, and in the Goſpell there is ſuch a liuing Commentary of his death and paſſion, that we doe not read but ſee him crucified.</p>
            <p>Many houres of conſultation had the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſpent in complotting <hi>his</hi> death, but all their deſignes were fruſtrated, for <hi>nondum venit hora,</hi> and when that time calculated by heauens appointment, was come; <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> is ſuborned, an Apoſtle that was his Treaſurer and his Almner; thou waſt deceiued <hi>Iudas, Vertue</hi> was his treaſure, <hi>Mercy</hi> was his dole; who to augment his pay, reſolues at once, to ſell his place and Maſter, and vnder-values <hi>him</hi> at ſo cheape a rate, that he ſets no price vpon the price of the world, but entertaines their owne proffer of <hi>thirty-peeces</hi> to become a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Traitor.</p>
            <p>Whileſt they ſtrike hands to betray him, the <hi>Lord</hi> remembers vs, inſtitutes the ſacrament of <hi>Grace,</hi> breaths forth diuine admonitions, makes his will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathes to his Diſciples <hi>his peace</hi> for a legacie, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and preſſures for an inheritance, againſt which he armeth them with heauenly habitations. <hi>Quo dulcius eſſe ſolet lumen Phoebi iam. iam cadentis;</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py men that were Auditors to this Sermon; then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth with a Hymne, which continued and ended with his progreſſe to Mount <hi>Oliuet:</hi> Was not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14031:11"/>now on earth, when <hi>Halleluiahs</hi> were chaunted by this holy Quire?</p>
            <p>Where, to meet the Traitor and his complices, <hi>He</hi> baulkes not the place <hi>Iudas</hi> knew was conſecrated by his cuſtomary deuotions, attended with three Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that had witneſſed his glory in the Mount; In a Garden vndergoes the pennance for <hi>Adams</hi> treſpaſſe in a garden; that the ſame place which was the neſt where ſin was firſt hatched, might be now the child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of grace and mercy; and where the premiſſes of our miſeries were, might be the concluſion of our misfortunes. There his <hi>ſoule</hi> is couched vnder the burthens of feare and ſorrow. <hi>The chaſtiſement of our peace is laid vpon him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath laid on him the iniquitie of vs all. Dauid</hi> fetched many penitent groanes; <hi>Caine</hi> belched forth words of deſpaire vnder this burthen; the heauens could not hold ſinfull <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> nor the earth <hi>Corah</hi> and his aſſociates, nor the water preſerue <hi>Pharach</hi> and his hoaſt. Maruell not then that <hi>Christ</hi> proſtrate in pangs, ſunke vnto the earth, bleſſing the ſame with his embracements, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>foot ſtoole</hi> his <hi>couch,</hi> where <hi>he</hi> findes, if not to lay his <hi>head,</hi> his <hi>face;</hi> like a worme <hi>hee</hi> crawles vpon the ground, and vpon that earth <hi>he</hi> is crucified without a <hi>Croſſe;</hi> feare and loue are the nailes, our ſinnes the thornes, his <hi>Fathers wrath</hi> the ſpeare to cruciate <hi>him,</hi> which cruſe a bleeding ſhower to raigne throughout all his pores, that in a cold night he ſweats without heat, and bleeds without a wound, all his body is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled with a crimſon dew; the very Vaines and Pores expediting our <hi>Sauiours</hi> will of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, not waiting the Tormentors furie, poure out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14031:11"/>the bloud of mercy.
<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Quàm frigidumerat peccatum quod tam calido indiguit lauacro.</hi> Foule ſinne that could not be clenſed but by ſuch a bath: That Sweat is not wipte off, but Hee falls into an Agony, in a counterconqueſt of affection if hee ſhall pitty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe or his people.</p>
            <p>Thrice doth he pray and thrice ſuffers an vnwilling willing repulſe; <hi>Si poſsibile, If it hee poſsible, let this Cup paſſe from me,</hi> was the voice of fleſh and bloud: but <hi>Fiat voluntas tua, Thy</hi> not <hi>my</hi> Will bee done, was the voice of a prompter Spirit. As a bitter Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Chriſt declines that Cup, but as beneficiall to vs, accepteth it. <hi>This Cup paſſe from me?</hi> Doth the Generall, quake and is the Souldier valiant? With vndaunted courage haue Martyrs imbraced the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Inſtruments of death;
<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Stat Martyr tripudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans &amp; triumphans licet corpore lacero, &amp; rimante la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera ferro:</hi> thoſe Bonefires to them golden Chariots to aſcend with <hi>Elias.</hi> That <hi>incendialis tunica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iones, lib.</hi> 1.</note> as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> termes it, a coat context of flames was put on willingly by many. But Chriſt vnderwent the ſting of death, they incountred death without a ſting. Death by Chriſt was once foiled, Hell by him once appalled, that the Relicts of that conqueſt are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with an eaſie onſet. Beſides, their puniſhments are ſo ſpiced and lenified with celeſtiall comfort, <hi>illis in poent est volunt as, in martyrio Coelum,</hi> that to theſe Chriſtian Stoicks their tortures are pleaſures, their martyrdom a Paradiſe. To <hi>Stephen</hi> the Heauens are opened, nor can that cloud of ſtones eclipſe him from ſeeing the Sun of Righteouſneſſe vpon his feet to aſſiſt him. To <hi>Peter</hi> a deliuering Angell, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14031:12"/>ſhakes off his chaines like duſt from his hands and feet; and asking no leaue of the Iaylors, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large him. Tis happineſſe to bee a Martyr; but to Chriſt afflicted what comfort is afforded? His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neuer ſo angry bent againſt him as now, when he perſonated vniuerſall ſinners. An Angell indeed lookes vpon him from Heauen, with a purpoſe to comfort him: alas, ſmall is the light that a <hi>Starre</hi> can yeeld when the <hi>Sunne</hi> is downe; and a ſorry ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, that a creature ſhall comfort his God, his Comforter.
<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> Therefore <hi>agnoſco vocem aegroti in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, agnoſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gallinam infirmantem cum Pullis, ſtupeo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerationem, expaneſco dignationem;</hi> that our Phiſician is ill, our Comforter deſolate, to me this mercy is an amazement, this infirmity a wonder.</p>
            <p>But hearke you Sir, What may you call thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that Chriſt did there indure? Our anſwer is, that he ſuffered all thoſe puniſhments for ſinne, that did reconcile vs to his <hi>Father.</hi> All thoſe, I ſay, that did neither preiudice the plenitude of ſanctitie or ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his ſacred perſon; but to ſay, that hell fire was indured by him, is a Doctrine fit for none, but him that hath made ſhipwracke of his faith, to land on ſhore his priuate fancies. How could it comply with Gods Sonne, to be ſubiected to that vengeance which was prepared for Deuills. Yet Chriſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went what the <hi>diuine Iuſtice</hi> could require, neither did the dignity of <hi>his perſon</hi> diſpenſe with any tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to make the paſſion of <hi>one</hi> auaileable for <hi>many.</hi> For if hee might haue diſpenſed with one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of extremity in puniſhment,
<note place="margin">4 <hi>Sent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 46. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>a.</hi> 4.</note> then with another, and ſo conſequently with all, as <hi>Scotus</hi> aptly noteth.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14031:12"/>So far as we are able to cleere this doubt, and acquit our ſelues of vniuſt imputation, obſerue, that ſinne is either inherent or aſſumed. To the firſt, there is euer annexed <hi>remorſe of conſcience,</hi> but not vnto the latter; Chriſt therefore aſſuming ſin by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not committing it, felt the puniſhment thereof, without the gnawings of the worme of Conſcience: againe, there are puniſhments due to ſinners which euer remaine in their ſtaine and guilt, or to thoſe which breake off their ſinnes by repentance: to the former, the Analogy of <hi>Iustice</hi> hath meaſured tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by the length of eternity, it being a well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionated right, that to thoſe, who if they had liued euer, would haue ſinned euer, to bee puniſhed for euer: but to thoſe which bury their temporary ſins in repentance, eternity of puniſhments belongeth not. Chriſt therefore ſuffering efficaciouſly for theſe, not for thoſe, ſatisfied his <hi>Father</hi> without eternity of puniſhments or deſpaire of recouery. Further, how Chriſt was exiled from his Fathers preſence, as his forlorne words vpon the Croſſe ſeeme to import. <hi>Scotus</hi> will informe vs, that <hi>affectione Iuſtitiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 <hi>Sent. d.</hi> 46. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>Reſp. ad princip. Arg.</hi>
               </note> he was euer vnited to his Father, becauſe he euer truſted, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and glorified him. But <hi>affectione commodi,</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light euer emergent from that diuine viſion, was for a time ſuſpended; his body and ſoule till the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, euer within ſight of the Deity, were ſtayed from glorification, ſo to make his ſoule and body ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of more ample ſorrow, was in the inſtant of <hi>his paſsion</hi> depriued of <hi>happineſſe.</hi> Though both theſe, ſaith <hi>Canus,</hi> may goe for Myracles, <hi>Chriſt</hi> was then forſaken of his Father, by deniall of protection and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14031:13"/>ſubtraction of Ioy, not otherwiſe. His ſoule hath not ended in theſe griefes, but new cruelties inuade his body. After theſe conflicts the butcherly <hi>Iewes</hi> attach him, and leade him as a Lambe to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, apprehending him whom mercy before had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended; as a Malefactor the true <hi>high Prieſt</hi> is brought before the falſe, &amp; from painted wall <hi>Annas</hi> diſmiſſed to <hi>Caiphas,</hi> a Prieſt as wiſe as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe, who ſpake more then he knew, yet the truth; where they binde his hands, buffet him with theirs, ſpit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his face, which the Angels deſire to contemplate; the Prieſts queſtion him, their ſeruants blinde him, thoſe, out of the ſuperfluity of contempt, theſe, of skorne; thoſe, to try if he were a God, theſe, if a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Accuſers are wanting, which in ſo wicked a generation cannot be long, who corrupt his words, change his meaning; for Chriſt ſaid not, <hi>Deſtruam Templum,</hi> but <hi>Soluite,</hi> I will deſtroy this Temple; but, deſtroy ye; neither added hee, <hi>Templum Dei,</hi> but ſimply, <hi>This Temple.</hi> Thirdly, hee meant his Body, not that materiall Fabrick wherein conſiſted their <hi>holy Oſtentation.</hi> This euening was famous with the reuolt and reconcilement of one Diſciple, as the next morning with the deſpaire of another: thus that day was ended.</p>
            <p>Their wrath went not downe with the Sunne, the next morning was to them a continuall night when they conſult to eclipſe the Sunne. <hi>Iudas,</hi> the firſt in treaſon, is the firſt in the Calender of reuenge; a tranſcendent ſunne, a Traitor <hi>Paramount:</hi> therefore he is his owne <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Executioner,</hi> his conſcience arraignes him, his owne hands do hang him. Paſſage
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14031:13"/>is denied that impious ſoule through thoſe lippes which had touched <hi>Chriſts:</hi> nor ſhall it aſcend ſo high towards heauen, but rip open a way by the violent rupture of his bowels to hell. <hi>Arius</hi> that killed his Godhead by denyall; <hi>Iudas</hi> his manhood by treaſon, are alike in puniſhment; yet it was a greater ſinne to kill himſelfe, then his Maſter.</p>
            <p>Theſe mentall murderers loath to act it with their owne hands, conuent <hi>him</hi> before <hi>Pilate.</hi> Where <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtands at the <hi>Roman</hi> tribunall, the Iudge delegated from God, more then <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſits in Commiſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; by him <hi>he</hi> is queſtioned to amazing ſilence. Iuſtly was the <hi>Lambe of God</hi> dumbe, and opened not his mouth before him that had ſhorne him with whips. <hi>Pilat</hi> after the expence of ſome cruelty, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to take off the <hi>Iewes,</hi> to lenifie and tame their cruelty, which like fire kept in with water ſprinkled, or a water-courſe ſtopt, breaks forth with greater fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Good Ieſus,</hi> how art thou now abuſed! New ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations are forged, new Knights of the Poſt procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to make <hi>thee</hi> a traitor to the <hi>Roman State. He</hi> that with Spittle cured the eyes of the blinde, is blinded with their ſpittle: who can number thoſe ſtripes wherwith they flea, and teare his body, one wound ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into another, that <hi>there is no health in his bones by reaſon of our ſinnes.</hi> Tyranny cloatheth him with one purple, died in the pureſt graine of his bloud; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine with another: a <hi>Reed is his Scepter,</hi> and a <hi>Crowne</hi> context with Thornes is beaten to his head; and with all the complement of ſcorne, on bended knees they ſalute <hi>him</hi> King. <hi>O Ieſus!</hi> was that frothy ſpittle the ointment, thoſe <hi>thornes</hi> thy <hi>Crowne,</hi> the <hi>Reed</hi> thy <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14031:14"/>the <hi>purple</hi> died and imbroidered with blood <hi>thy royall robes:</hi> or becauſe <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne brought forth <hi>thornes,</hi> muſt it be <hi>thy</hi> penance to weare them? Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull people, thus watred with his bloud, bring forth nothing but <hi>Thornes</hi> to crowne <hi>him: conſpuunt in leprefu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ugauerunt vt latronem, deriſerunt vt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Pilate</hi> perſiſting to take off the edge of their malice, expoſeth him to be commiſerated, with <hi>Ecce homo,</hi> ſufficiently puniſhed; <hi>Ecce Rex veſter,</hi> ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly derided; then pleading the benefit of their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, is deſirous that <hi>Chriſt</hi> might be pardoned vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on courſe, but theſe pacifications are but whetſtones of a ſharper and more incenſed hatred. <hi>Barrabas</hi> that brought many from life to death, is preferred before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that brought more from death to life; and no maruell, like will to like, murderers to a murderer. An outcry is raiſed, <hi>Crucifie him, crucifie him:</hi> twice <hi>Cruelfie,</hi> as if they thought one <hi>Croſſe</hi> too little for <hi>him;</hi> Inconſtant fauour of man, their Anthemes of <hi>Hoſanna</hi> and <hi>Benedictus</hi> not long ſince ioyfully ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, are conuerted into <hi>tragicall</hi> notes of <hi>Crucifie him.</hi> If <hi>Pilat</hi> be indulgent, they goe neere to proclaime him traitor, to auoid which ſuſpition, he chooſeth to be an vniuſt Iudge, rather then ſuppoſed a diſloyall ſubiect: by his doome he allots him to the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points the Souldiers his executioners, and the Prieſts his Ouerſters.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Chriſt</hi> goeth the dolorous way, beares his <hi>Croſſe</hi> till he fainted, that bore <hi>him</hi> till <hi>he</hi> dyed, where malice in <hi>them,</hi> longing as much as mercy in <hi>him</hi> for accompliſhment; to make haſte permit him an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iutor.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14031:14"/>A guilty conſcience doubteth want of time, therefore diſpatcheth haſtily. Where the women as as <hi>he</hi> went, ſtrew the way with teares, whom he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to ſpend when occaſion ſhallſerue, to ſtill their plaint and to ſtay their weeping, as if ſome treſpaſſe were in their teares, or ſome ſinne in their ſorrow: when in the rage of ſlaughter Infants blood ſhall be more plentifull then Mothers teares, and a ſcreeching voice ſhall be heard in <hi>Hteruſalem,</hi> many <hi>Rachels</hi> wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>for their children, and would not be comforted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Muſt no other death ſtint their malice but the <hi>Croſſe?</hi> others they had in practiſe, as the Towell, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and beheading, more fauourable, and ſutable to their Nation; will they pollute a <hi>Iew</hi> with a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> death? <hi>He was made obedient to the death of the Croſſe,</hi> a degree beyond death. <hi>Magnacrudelitas, non ſolum occidere, ſed &amp; crucifigere quaerunt, vt morte vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aretur producta,</hi> ſaith venerable <hi>Bede:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull.</note> the Croſſe <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifigendi corporis machina,</hi> the engine of torture, a ſlow death, ſpinning out paine into a longer threed, where <hi>his</hi> owne weight becomes his owne affliction, vpon this racke <hi>dinumerauerunt omnia oſſa mea;</hi> They ſum vp the number of his bones, anatomize his body, his armes and legges racked with violent puls, hands and feet boared with nailes, his ſide wounded with a ſpeare, the whole body torne with ſtripes, and goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with blood; with what words ſhall I complaine of their ſauageneſſe?
<note place="margin">Lactant.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> extended all the nerues of Eloquence, and crucified his inuentions to expreſſe the quality of theſe paines, yet was <hi>non-p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt</hi> at his <hi>Gauintan</hi> Croſſe: yet hitherto their malice brought our Sauiour.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14031:15"/>
            <p> And that at the ſolemne time of the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> when <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was full of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Proſelytes;</hi> they kill the Lambe of <hi>God</hi> without a <hi>figure,</hi> their malice making way for the diuine diſpenſation, <hi>for Chriſt our paſseouer is offred for vs, &amp;c.</hi> And to fulfill their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with a Propheſie, they crucifie him with theeues, where the one a <hi>Doeg</hi> obdurate wounds <hi>him</hi> with his tongue, and hath Iuſtice; the <hi>other</hi> in a holy <hi>Catastro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe,</hi> doth bleſſe <hi>God and dye:</hi> Were my ſoule ſo happy a <hi>felon</hi> as to ſteale <hi>Paradiſe</hi> at the laſt; I would not feare any temporall arraignment to dye ſuch a ſinner, or to be condemned for ſuch a thiefe.</p>
            <p>The witneſſe of all this, and chiefe mourner was the <hi>Bleſsed virgin: Nature</hi> &amp; <hi>Grace</hi> are the welſprings whence flow ſuch riuers of teares for her innocent ſonne; now <hi>Simeons</hi> Propheſie is made good: A ſword of compaſſion doth pierce her heart; Can ſuch a mother forget ſuch a ſonne? by a reflect act her hands and feet with his are pierced, her ſide woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and head bruiſed with thornes, as if but one ſoule in two bodies. <hi>Oh my Lord!</hi> thy griefe was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that euer was in man, and mine as great as euer happened to woman. The very dumbe Creatures cry out of theſe paines; the renting of his body rends the vaile of the Temple; the digging into his ſide opens the Monuments; the cry of him dying awakes the dead; the immouable earth doth quake for feare of thoſe feares; the Sun is aſhamed to ſhew his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when the Father of lights was darkned with ſuch diſgrace; the Heauens diſcolour their beauties, and ſuiting themſelues to their makers fortune are in mourning robes when the lampe of heauen is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14031:15"/>Ingratefull Nation, the Sunne will not ſhine vpon them, but is immantled with a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous eclipſe, and Sympathizing with the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe, will not appeare in <hi>Glory,</hi> when the <hi>Lord of Glory</hi> is thus diſgraced:
<note place="margin">Bonau.</note> 
               <hi>Solus homo non compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur pro quo ſolo Chriſtus patitur.</hi> Onely man is bereft of compaſſion, for whom onely <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnderwent this <hi>Paſsion.</hi> I except the <hi>Centurion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>qui vitam agnouit in morte,</hi> who in the ſhadow of death eſpied the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Deitie. <hi>Surely this man was the Sonne of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Chriſt hauing out-cryed his torments, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for reliefe, and at his death for forgiueneſſe to his enemies; <hi>emiſit ſpiritum non amiſit,</hi> willingly yeelds to nature, and offers vp a broken heart and a troubled ſpirit to his Father for the worlds redemption: O ſtrange <hi>Phyſicke</hi> where the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> muſt bleed! and a ſtranger Conqueſt, where the Conquerour muſt dye, and God would take no other ſatisfaction. The wit of Heathen Religion pacified their Gods with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and of greater price of greater efficacie. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine placaſtis ventos, &amp;c.</hi> The Childrens paſſage through the fire to <hi>Molech</hi> was thought a holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; but here is a myſtery, <hi>God to offer himſelfe,</hi> and men to kill him: <hi>Noua hoſtia nouo imponitur alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, &amp; crux Chriſti non templi fit ara ſed mundi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo:</hi> this <hi>Catholike Sacrifice</hi> is offred vpon Mount <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary,</hi> the altar of the world; O the Miracle of mercy to quicken vs! <hi>The Lord</hi> is, view his worth in the end of my Text. <hi>The Lord of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall that Deity,
<note place="margin">Lord of glory.</note> which principally reſides in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be faſtned to a croſſe on earth? truely, though
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14031:16"/>the Deitie be impatible, yet by Hypoſtaticall vnion, it conſtituted, and made vp that Perſon which was qualified to paſſion, and that ſo well compacted and put together, that death could not diuorce that vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The godhead hath not fleſh and bloud, yet God, <hi>he</hi> bled for vs, <hi>Qui redemit nos ſanguine ſuo:</hi> our ſinnes were at ſo high a rate, that nothing but the blood of the Lord of glory could purchaſe vs.</p>
            <p>This vnion conſiſteth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vndiuided, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inſeperable, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> without locall diſtance, ſaith <hi>Damaſcene:</hi> as a branch in the ſtocke, as light in the Sunne, as an accident in a ſubiect is the humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſuſtained by the Deitie. The Catholike Faith go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpright betwixt <hi>Eutiches</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> bending neither to the right hand of naturall confuſion, or to the left of perſonall diuorce. Now, <hi>Quaecunque in vno ſuppoſito vniuntur, illa deſe inuicem poſſunt praedicari.</hi> Our Sauiours perſon is inueſted with the properties of either nature; hence flow the <hi>concrete predicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of natures, God</hi> is <hi>man;</hi> and the abſtract commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of properties to the ſubiect Chriſt, is infiniteneſſe. In this marriage the humane nature is in the perſon enſtated with all the diuine Royalties; and that is ſo indulgent, as to aſſume her infirmities, that we may ſay, Chriſt-God-Man made the world, Chriſt-Man-God redeemed it. Here is the root of the infiniteneſſe of his merits; <hi>Principium quo,</hi> the ſubiect wherein he ſuffered was the humane nature; but the <hi>principium quod,</hi> the ſoule which did enable and informe it was the Deity.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sent.</hi> 3. <hi>d.</hi> 19.</note> Chriſt did <hi>elicere acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones ex ſuppoſito,</hi> ſaith <hi>Scotus,</hi> performe his taske in proper perſon. So by that meanes, reconciled infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14031:16"/>to all his actions. Infinite not in reſpect of the act, but Perſon, <hi>The Lord of glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gabriel.</hi> 3.5.19. <hi>d. q. 19. d. q. vnica.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord of glory,</hi> and yet crucified! Neuer was <hi>glory</hi> ſo eclipſed, here is <hi>Honour</hi> aſhamed, <hi>Maieſty</hi> affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Innocence</hi> guilty, <hi>health</hi> ſicke, the <hi>Sunne</hi> in the night, a vailed <hi>Deity.</hi> In mount <hi>Tabor</hi> Chriſt was apparelled like himſelfe, a man might reade Maieſty in his countenance, but in Mount <hi>Caluary</hi> all is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenebrated. Chriſt, like his Spouſe the Church, is blacke, but comely. The Croſſe <hi>nigredo eſt ſed forma, &amp; ſimilitudo Domini.</hi> Goe vnto <hi>Eſay, Hee hath no forme nor comlineſſe, there is no beauty in him.</hi> The ſable Curtaines by that Prophet are drawne vpon him: Haue recourſe vnto <hi>Dauid, Thou art fairer then the children of men, grace is powred into thy lips:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Intu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere ſane pannis ſordidum, plagis liuidum, illitum ſputis, pallidum morte, &amp; nigrum vel tunc profecto fatebere;</hi> to ſee him thus conſpuicated, thy wit will ſerue thee to confeſſe his blackneſſe; but aske the Apoſtles whom they ſaw in the Mount, or the Angels whom they deſire to ſee, thou wilt ſoone recognize him to be <hi>the Lord of glory. Ergo formoſus in ſe, niger prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te;</hi> ſo comely in <hi>himſelfe,</hi> ſo blacke for <hi>thee:</hi> thus crucified <hi>he</hi> was without diſparagement to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Non eſt fastidita humilitas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo.</note> 
               <hi>quia nec imminuta Maieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; nihil nocuit naturae inuiolabili quod paſsibili oportehat inferri.</hi> All theſe paſſions truly vndergone by <hi>him,</hi> did no whit impeach his Deity. So, <hi>Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum eſt,</hi> it is finiſhed, and with it my Meditations: there is remaining a ſhort concluſion which deſires to finde and leaue you attentiue.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14031:17"/>
            <p> YOu haue heard me relate the greateſt crime that euer was committed, wherein I know not if the Art of Tyranny were greater to inuent, or Chriſts patience to endure. The <hi>Heire</hi> is ſlaine, but the <hi>Iewes</hi> haue loſt the <hi>inheritance.</hi> This is the <hi>medulla,</hi> and bleſſedneſſe of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that God ſet more by vs, then his Sonne, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> loſt his life in ſeeking vs. <hi>Nos tanto redimimur pretio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo.</note> 
               <hi>nos tanto curamur impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio;</hi> ſo dearely did he ranſome vs. <hi>Is it nothing vnto you, all ye that paſſe by, Behold and ſee, if there bee any ſorrow like to my ſorrow which is done vnto me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord hath afflicted mee in the day of his fierce anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet to conſider Chriſt as a man of ſorrow, &amp; not a Sauiour of ſinners, that <hi>his</hi> wounds were not our ſalues, yeelds but a melancholike contemplation; but when we call to mind that this was our ranſome, and how euery ſtripe that razed his Fleſh doth cure our ſoules: How the bloud of compaſſion ranne in Chriſt: <hi>nec deſunt foramina per quae effluat;</hi> Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it pipes are not wanting for transfuſion, not of bloud but mercy; with all our hearts we pray, <hi>His Bloud be vpon vs and our children.</hi> In the Sea of ſinne let vs caſt Anchor vpon this Rocke; be thy ſinnes neuer ſo great,
<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> it is able to ſupport them. <hi>Turbatur Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſed non perturbabitur;</hi> the ſting of ſinne is taken out by our Sauiours Paſſion, ſo that though the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereof be bitter, yet the rehearſall of Chriſts Paſſions is farre ſweeter, wherein <hi>Quot vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera tot ora,</hi> ſo many wounds, ſo many ſpeaking and interceding tongues, pleading thy right at the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-ſeat, <hi>Lord, whither ſhall we then goe?</hi> Heere is a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14031:17"/>
               <hi>Iubilee</hi> of grace: let Rome expect an influence of goodneſſe from the Starres, we deſire but the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe to be our light, our heat, our life. <hi>Quaeris Alcidae parem, nemo eſt niſi ipſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca in Theb.</note> Let our ſoules periſh if He cannot ſaue them.</p>
            <p>Beware your ſinnes make you not incapable. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus waſhed all his Diſciples feet, yet all were not cleane: though from the <hi>Center of Caluary</hi> lines of mercy are drawne to the vtmoſt parts of the earth, yet all the world is not within the Circle of pardon. The beſt Phyſike hath not its efficacy vpon ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed patients, <hi>Quicquid recipitur, &amp;c.</hi> proues true in Diuinity: I ſhall goe beyond my Commiſſion to tell you, He hath made Saluation as common as the light of the Sunne or breath of our Noſtrells; God is no Prodigall of his mercy: inuert that ſpeech of <hi>Piſo</hi> in <hi>Tacitus, Perdere ſcit, donare neſcit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſtor.</hi> 1.</note> hee is bountifull, not profuſe, and his goodneſſe obſerues a Method. Chriſts pains were not extenſiuely infinite, ſo not auailable for ſuch ſinners, of whoſe iniquity there is no end. Our ſins indeed betraied him into ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hands, <hi>who crucifie vnto themſelues the Son of God afreſh, and put him to open ſhame.</hi> Euery ſin is a naile, a thorne, a Speare; &amp; euery ſinner, a Iew, a <hi>Iudas,</hi> and a <hi>Pilat.</hi> Be not incouraged to ſin, and then think to take Sanctuary at a Sauiour; iniure not Chriſt ſo much, as to make him the foundation of thy ſinfull life, who loſt his to extinguiſh it; preſumptuous ſinners! that put themſelues vnder the protection of a Redeemer, and ſo thinke to eſcape the areſt: Surely, to tender Chriſt the complement of our lips with corrupt hearts, is like the Souldiers, to proſtrate our ſelues
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14031:18"/>before him in ſcorne.
<note place="margin">Bera.</note> Deferre not to be good vpon hopes, <hi>I tu &amp; quaere ſalutem in medio Gehennae, quae ſemel operata eſt in medio terrae;</hi> this life is our Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt to reape the fruit of <hi>his</hi> merits. Finally, Chriſt hath left vs an example to <hi>crucifie the world with the luſts thereof;</hi> for, <hi>Quid eſt volaticum huius mundi gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium?</hi> This world is a fleeting good, a winged Ioy. But <hi>ſpes Reſurrectionis faſtidium eſt mortis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian.</hi> The Saints contemne death, who haue a part in the ſecond Reſurrection: where they ſhall be crowned, not with Thornes but Glory; and ſing praiſes to Ieſus, <hi>the Lord of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14031:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
